Guide to the Howard E. Buswell papers and photographs 1822-1965
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Howard E. Buswell papers and photographs
1822-1965
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0017buswell
Buswell, Howard
35 Linear Ft.
The collection consists of primary source material collected by self-trained historian Howard E. Buswell during his lifetime. The items included in the collection cover nearly all aspects of social and economic life of the lower Nooksack Valley and North Puget Sound areas in Washington State from the time of the first contact between white settlers and Native Americans to the early decades of the twentieth century. Buswell was also interested in the Lummi Indian culture and the collection contains a good deal of source material related to the history of this tribe.
Howard E. Buswell was born on April 22, 1895, on his family's farm near Ferndale, Washington. In 1906, the Buswell family moved to land near Marietta, Washington on Bellingham Bay. There, except for a short period during and right after World War I, Howard Buswell lived out the remainder of his life.
Buswell's early education was acquired at various elementary and high schools in Ferndale, Marietta, and Bellingham, Washington. During World War I he served in the United States Navy, and on discharge he continued for a short time at sea in the merchant navy. He then worked briefly in the insurance industry with the Metropolitan Life Company.
Two years at the State College of Washington, now Washington State University, in the early 1920s were followed by a year at the Bellingham Normal School, now Western Washington University. After obtaining his teaching certificate at the Normal School, he began teaching elementary school in Cosmopolis, Washington in Grays Harbor County. Poor health, however, cut short his career in education and he was forced to retire.
For the remaining forty or so years of his life, he lived on the family farm, raising chickens and processing cider in association with his brother, Ray. It was during these years that he began his research into local history, undertaking many "projects", as he called them. These "projects" took him to libraries, museums, and court houses across the country, and led to the voluminous correspondence with archivists and librarians in many of the major repositories in the United States and several in Canada as well. He intended to write a local history book on Marietta and the nearby Lummi Reservation, however, he was still gathering materials at the time of his death in 1965 and his book was never completed.
The Buswell papers and photographs consists of primary source material collected by self-trained historian Howard Buswell during his lifetime. Researchers must pay particular attention to the fact that in his collecting efforts and in his writings Buswell provides an interpretation of history that reflects his own biases and the time period in which he lived. The items included in the collection cover nearly all aspects of social and economic life of the lower Nooksack Valley and North Puget Sound areas in Washington State from the time of the first contact between white settlers and Native Americans to the early decades of the twentieth century. He was also interested in the Lummi culture and the collection contains a good deal of source material related to the history of this tribe.
The collection consists of thirty boxes of material including correspondence, duplicates of primary source material, indexes and lists, business records, transcripts of interviews, copies of legal documents, scrapbooks and newspaper clipping. The collection also includes 16 boxes of photographs, 10 boxes of microfilm, over 2000 maps, and 3 boxes of reel to reel audio tapes of oral history interviews.
The correspondence begins in 1938 and ends in 1965 with the main purpose of assembling materials and other evidence on pioneer settlement in the Marietta/Lummi area. The bulk of the letters, however, relate to historical materials held in various archives and other repositories or else are inquiries to the latter about such materials. The correspondence is arranged in chronological order with the original letter attached to the reply. The indexes and lists are, for the most part, lists and indexes of various materials Howard Buswell collected. It should be noted though that the present organization of the Buswell papers and photographs is often radically different from the arrangement suggested by the indexes. The Bernard N. McDonough business records include miscellaneous private and business letters, receipts and bills, various legal documents, and a number of account books kept in McDonough's Marietta store. The legal documents and papers have been arranged in part according to subject, in part according to type, and in part according to the court of origin. They are composed of a variety of legal records ranging from business records to transcripts of select court cases.
The collection is organized in accordance with the following series arrangement:
Series I- Correspondence, 1938-1965
Series II- Original Writings, Undated
Series III- Biographical Materials, Undated
Series IV- Interviews, Undated
Series V- Indian Materials, 1867-1964
Series VI- Indexes and Lists, Undated
Series VII- Whatcom County Historical Materials, 1858-1957
Series VIII- Pacific Northwest Historical Materials, 1946-1959
Series IX- The Bernard N. McDonough Business Records, 1874-1913
Series X- Legal Documents and Papers, 1822-1925
Series XI- Scrapbooks, 1941-1965
Series XII- Newspaper Clippings, 1891-1975
Series XIII - Microfilm, 1865-1946
Series XIV - Audio Collection, 1956-1964
Series XV - Map Collection, Undated
Series XVI - Photograph Collection, Undated
The Collection is open to the public.
Ray Buswell donated the records of his brother, Howard Buswell, to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies in 1975.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Buswell, Howard--Archives.
McDonough, Bernard N.--Archives.
Indians of North America -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County; Salmon canning industry -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County; Salmon fisheries -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County; Mines and mineral resources -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources.; Mines and mineral resources -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Maps.; Frontier and pioneer life -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.; Lummi Indians -- Washington (State) -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.; Railroads -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Maps.; Railroads -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.; Lumber trade -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.; Lumber trade -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources.; Nooksack River Valley -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.; Nooksack River Valley -- Washington (State) -- Whatcom County -- History -- Sources -- Maps.; Lummi Reservation (Wash.) -- History -- Sources -- Photographs.
Washington (State); Maps; Oral Histories; Photographs; Sound Recordings; Anthropology; Fisheries and Wildlife; Forestry and Forestry Products; Logging; Mines and Mineral Resources; Native Americans; Pioneers
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Correspondence, 1938-1965; Series I
  - Correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Letters to and from J.M. Edson of Bellingham, Undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Letters to and from Robert Emmett Hawley of Lynden, Undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Letters to and from Major J.S. Matthews, Vancouver (BC) City Archives, Undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Ray Buswell Letters, Undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, Undated (Box-folder 1/11)
- Original Writings, Undated; Series II
  - "The Lummi River" I (10 draft chapters), Undated (Box-folder 2/1)
  - "The Lummi River" II (12 draft chapters), Undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Lummi Tales, Undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Journal and Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Writer's Projects, Undated (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Drafts of writings on Northwest Washington topics, Undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Archaeological notes and writings on Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Manuscript: "Investigations of the Prehistoric Human Remains of the Lower Nooksack", Undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Manuscript: "California Report." This includes comments on historical materials found in the Bancroft Library at Berkeley and the Los Angeles Public Library, Undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, Undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Notes on collections in various libraries and museums, Undated (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Notes on miscellaneous Northwest Washington historical matters, Undated (Box-folder 2/12)
- Biographical Materials, Undated; Series III
  - Notecards on the biographical materials, Undated (Box-folder 3/1)
  - John Allen, Undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Solomon Allen (I), Undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Solomon Allen (II), Undated (Box-folder 3/4)
  - William T. Ballou, Undated (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Ellis Barnes (I), Undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Ellis Barnes (II), Undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - John Barnes, Undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Carl Bell, Undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - John Broyles, Undated (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Ray Buswell, Undated (Box-folder 3/11)
  - A.C. Buswell, Undated (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Eugene Canfield, Undated (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Francis Celestine, Undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Phillip M. Clark, Undated (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Edward Collier, Undated (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Dan Cooper, Undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Harrison Cowden, Undated (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Lyman Cutler, Undated (Box-folder 4/6)
  - David and Martha Dealy, Undated (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Abner Dunn, Undated (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Edward Eldridge, Undated (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Teresa Eldridge, Undated (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Charles and Lizzie Frank, Undated (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Peter Gallagher, Undated (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Roland Gamwell, Undated (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Major Edson Gerry, Undated (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Alfred Hamilton, Undated (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Dan Harris, Undated (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Lida Hawley, Undated (Box-folder 4/17)
  - James G. Hedge, Undated (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Eric A. Hegg, Undated (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Ella Higginson, Undated (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Charles H. Hurlbut, Undated (Box-folder 4/21)
  - William Jarman, Undated (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Charley Kahana, Undated (Box-folder 4/23)
  - Lawrence "Smuggler" Kelly, Undated (Box-folder 4/24)
  - William King Lear, Undated (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Mary Frances Lysle, Undated (Box-folder 4/26)
  - Frank Mahoney, Undated (Box-folder 4/27)
  - Alexander Maclean, Undated (Box-folder 4/28)
  - Bernard McDonough, Undated (Box-folder 4/29)
  - John Munro, Undated (Box-folder 4/30)
  - Pardon and Israel O'Brien, Undated (Box-folder 4/31)
  - Russell V. Peabody, Undated (Box-folder 4/32)
  - Gage Abner Pence, Undated (Box-folder 4/33)
  - Captain George E. Pickett, Undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Frank Reid and "Soapy" Smith, Undated (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Charles E. and Marie W. Roberts, Undated (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Captain Henry Roeder, Undated (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Chris Siegel, Undated (Box-folder 5/5)
  - John A. Tennant, Undated (Box-folder 5/6)
  - David E. Tuck, Undated (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Guy E. Van Horn, Undated (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Moses Yunkin, Undated (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Items, Undated (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Articles relating to Whatcom County residents by P.R. Jeffcott, Undated (Box-folder 5/11)
- Interviews, Undated; Series IV
  - John Allen, Undated (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Solomon Allen, Undated (Box-folder 5/13)
  - W.E. Banks and E.A. Hegg, Undated (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Henry Barrett, Undated (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Carl Bell, Undated (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Mrs. John Berger and Mrs. C.L. Annis, Undated (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Mrs. Jack Bizer, Undated (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Charley Bond, Undated (Box-folder 5/19)
  - Mrs. Irene (Taylor) Bond on James H. Taylor, Undated (Box-folder 5/20)
  - Mrs. George Boone, Undated (Box-folder 5/21)
  - Mrs. Johanna Brown, Undated (Box-folder 5/22)
  - Harry S. Byther, Undated (Box-folder 5/23)
  - Mrs. Hallie Lysle Campbell, Undated (Box-folder 5/24)
  - Julius Charles, Undated (Box-folder 5/25)
  - Phil Clark, Undated (Box-folder 5/26)
  - Mrs. John Clearwater, Undated (Box-folder 5/27)
  - Mrs. Lelah Jackson Edson, Undated (Box-folder 5/28)
  - Mrs. Frances U. Evans, Undated (Box-folder 5/29)
  - Mrs. Nettie (James L.) Fox, Undated (Box-folder 5/30)
  - Roland Gamwell, Undated (Box-folder 5/31)
  - Bert Garris, Undated (Box-folder 5/32)
  - William Gibson, Undated (Box-folder 5/33)
  - Mrs. Sam W. Harden, Undated (Box-folder 5/34)
  - Robert Emmett Hawley, Undated (Box-folder 5/35)
  - Edmund S. Hincks, Undated (Box-folder 5/36)
  - Mrs. Howard Holmes, Undated (Box-folder 5/37)
  - Charles H. Hurlbut Sr., Undated (Box-folder 5/38)
  - Peter James, Undated (Box-folder 5/39)
  - Percival R. Jeffcott and his wife, Undated (Box-folder 5/40)
  - Sidney Jones, Undated (Box-folder 5/41)
  - Mr. Johnston, Undated (Box-folder 5/42)
  - Charley Kahana, Undated (Box-folder 5/43)
  - Delia Keeler, Undated (Box-folder 5/44)
  - Dr. William Keyes, Undated (Box-folder 5/45)
  - L.A. Kibbe, Undated (Box-folder 5/46)
  - Mabel Munroe Noffsinger Lameraux, Undated (Box-folder 5/47)
  - Mrs. Anne Larson, Undated (Box-folder 5/48)
  - Mrs. James Scott Lashua, Undated (Box-folder 5/49)
  - Nellie Lee, Undated (Box-folder 5/50)
  - Jim Lewis, Undated (Box-folder 5/51)
  - Mrs. Fred Loveland, Undated (Box-folder 5/52)
  - Mrs. Malmberg, Undated (Box-folder 5/53)
  - Retta Markwood, Undated (Box-folder 5/54)
  - Chief August Martin and John Brown, Undated (Box-folder 5/55)
  - Mrs. Emily Mohrmann, Undated (Box-folder 5/56)
  - Mrs. John Morrison, Undated (Box-folder 5/57)
  - Mrs. John A. Munch, Undated (Box-folder 5/58)
  - Harvey Nelson, Undated (Box-folder 5/59)
  - J.B. Nicholls, Undated (Box-folder 5/60)
  - Will D. Pratt, Undated (Box-folder 5/61)
  - Mrs. Annie Tawes Ray, Undated (Box-folder 5/62)
  - Ira Robinson, Undated (Box-folder 5/63)
  - H. and Albert C. Rossell, Undated (Box-folder 5/64)
  - Jack Sheilds, Undated (Box-folder 5/65)
  - Fred Siegel, Undated (Box-folder 5/66)
  - Henry Slater, Undated (Box-folder 5/67)
  - Mrs. Fred Smith, Undated (Box-folder 5/68)
  - Julia Wynn, Undated (Box-folder 5/69)
  - Walter Wallace, Undated (Box-folder 5/73)
  - Frank Wiffler, Undated (Box-folder 5/74)
  - Mrs. Jennie (Stand) Robins Winter, Undated (Box-folder 5/75)
  - Miscellaneous items, Undated (Box-folder 5/76)
- Indian Materials, 1867-1964; Series V
  - Items on Indian languages including Chinook Jargon, Undated (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Indian nomenclature, Undated (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Indian Treaties, Undated (Box-folder 6/3)
  - The Point Eliot Treaty, Undated (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Lummi Indians, Undated (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Lummi Indians, Undated (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Lummi Indians, Undated (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Lummi Indians, Undated (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Lummi Indians: Jefferson v. Old Polan Case, Undated (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Lummi Stommish programs, circa 1955-1964 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - "The Lummi Indians of the Pacific Northwest" by John Johnston, Undated (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Manuscript: Wayne Suttles "Post White Culture Change at Lummi", Undated (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Lummi School, D.A.R. Essays (Contest), Undated (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Manuscript: Frances Mayhew, "Essays on Indian Topics" 1931, Undated (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Photostat: letter of Edward Eldridge to the Superintendent of Indian Affairs, 1867 August 8 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Totem Poles of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 6/16)
  - "Squaw Men" of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Lummi Indian Reservation allotments, 1883 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Handwritten notes on Indian life, Undated (Box-folder 6/19)
  - Letter from Hugh Eldridge to Roland Gamwell on Indian lore and life, 1924 November 20 (Box-folder 6/20)
  - Notes on Lummi Indians, Undated (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Notes on Indians, mainly Lummi, Undated (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Notes on matters conchological, archaeological, and geological, Undated (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Buswell materials on Indian artifacts, Undated (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Indian canoes and canoe races, Undated (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Lummi Indian basketwork project, Undated (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Letter from Andrew Mattson to Charles M. Buchanan, Superintendent Tulalip Reservation, on Indian tidelands, 1914 March 4 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Buswell's notes on Theodore Winthrop's The Canoe and the Saddle, Undated (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Report of the Planning Committee of the Tulalip Indian Agency, 1944-1957 (Box-folder 7/9)
  - H.D. McCullough, "Tulalip Ten-Year Program Summary", 1944 (Box-folder 7/10)
  - Materials pertaining to Dr. Charles Milton Buchanan on Indian matters, Undated (Box-folder 7/11)
  - Skagit County: Sale of Liquor to Indians, 1893-1897 (Box-folder 7/12)
  - Lummi Indian Census Materials, 1885-1950 (Box-folder 7/13)
- Indexes and Lists, Undated; Series VI
  - Book Lists, Undated (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Book reviews and book notices, Undated (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Index to the Charles H. Hurlbut Papers (it should be noted that these papers comprise the bulk of the legal documents contained in boxes 19-27 inclusive), Undated (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Indexes to interviews, Undated (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Notes on the McDonough Business Records, Undated (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Items relating to Buswell's map collection, Undated (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Notes on the microfilm and photostats in the collection, Undated (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Notes on miscellaneous published works, Undated (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Newspaper collection list, Undated (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Lists of photographs in the collection, Undated (Box-folder 8/10)
  - U.S.G.S. indexes, Undated (Box-folder 8/11)
  - Miscellaneous indexes and lists, Undated (Box-folder 8/12)
  - Miscellaneous Notecards, Undated (Box-folder 8/13)
  - Miscellaneous Notecards, Undated (Box-folder 8/14)
  - Binder with Collection index (inaccurate), Undated (Box-folder 8/15)
- Whatcom County Historical Materials, 1858-1957; Series VII
  - County Auditor: Notes on tax rolls, etc., Undated (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Brickyards of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Bridges and ferries of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Cattle brands, Undated (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Cemeteries and burial grounds, Undated (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Checklist of suggested field trips for scouts, Undated (Box-folder 9/6)
  - County Commissioners: proceedings, Undated (Box-folder 9/7)
  - County Clerk and County Treasurer: various items, Undated (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Notes on donation claims and homestead claims, Undated (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Fisheries and fish traps, Undated (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Livestock items, Undated (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Nooksack River: various items and notes, Undated (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Nooksack River: various items and notes, Undated (Box-folder 9/13)
  - Old Settlers' Association of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 9/14)
  - Pamplets and Business Cards, Undated (Box-folder 9/15)
  - Warrants, 1889-1891 (Box-folder 9/16)
  - Checks, 1901-1940 (Box-folder 9/17)
  - Taxpayers' League letters on Bellingham Prohibition Vote, 1910 (Box-folder 9/18)
  - Miscellaneous items, Undated (Box-folder 9/19)
  - Original survey of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Photographers of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Pioneer settlers of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Post offices of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Railroads of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Probate records of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Roads of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Schools of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Sheriff of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Shipwrecks, mainly in Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Statistics of the 1860 Census: Whatcom County, compiled by Mrs. John B. Mayer, D.A.R., 1931-1932 (Box-folder 10/11)
  - Steamboats and river boats of Whatcom County, Undated (Box-folder 10/12)
  - Steamboats- Captain James W. Tarte, Undated (Box-folder 10/13)
  - The Telegraph Road, Undated (Box-folder 10/14)
  - The Whatcom Trail and the Fraser gold rush, Undated (Box-folder 10/15)
  - Miscellaneous Materials- Land claims, Lower Nooksack- Marietta, Lummi, Undated (Box-folder 10/16)
  - Edson-Gerry: Formation of Memorial College: Younkin-Dealy-Monroe Land Claims, Undated (Box-folder 10/17)
  - Fishing License Applications, Undated (Box-folder 10/18)
  - Programs and Pamphlets, Undated (Box-folder 10/19)
  - Envelopes - Addressed and Stamped, Undated (Box-folder 10/20)
  - Receipts and Accounts, Undated (Box-folder 10/21)
  - Bellingham: Housing Tour, 1957 May 21 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Manuscript: "Historic Buildings of Bellingham and Whidbey Island" Compiled by Henry S. Byther, 1935 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - City of Bellingham: General Election Poll Book, Tally Sheet and Official Census, 1904 November (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Items on Eliza Island, Undated (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Items on Fairhaven, Undated (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Items on Lummi Island, Undated (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Items on Marietta, Undated (Box-folder 11/7)
  - The churches of Marietta, Undated (Box-folder 11/8)
  - New Whatcom items: notices, ordinances, Undated (Box-folder 11/9)
  - New Whatcom: additional items, Undated (Box-folder 11/10)
  - New Whatcom: roll book of members of the New Whatcom Fire Department, 1895 June (Box-folder 11/11)
  - Lists of bicycle licenses, 1899-1901 (Box-folder 11/11)
  - Legal Agreement: City of New Whatcom and Charles E. Lind, 1900 (Box-folder 11/12)
  - W.G. Hawkins Papers, Undated (Box-folder 11/13)
  - Military affairs pertaining to Whatcom County, circa 1850s (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Lists of Washington Territorial Volunteers, Undated (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Photostat: Contract with Fitzhugh and Warbass to construct the Military Road from Whatcom to Fort Bellingham, 1858 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Copy of Inspector-General Mansfield's report on the Inspection of the Post of Semi-ah-moo, 1858 December (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Items on Fort Bellingham, Undated (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Notes on local newspapers (Whatcom County), Undated (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Notes on the Marietta Messenger, Undated (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Notes on the Northern Light and the Gazette (Victoria), Undated (Box-folder 12/8)
  - KGMI radio editorials, Undated (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Whatcom County Post Office Records (Copies from National Archives, map of Ferndale), circa 1866-1909 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Pacific Northwest Historical Materials, 1946-1959; Series VIII
  - Exploration of the Pacific Northwest, particularly the Spanish explorations, Undated (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Pacific Northwest river boats, Undated (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Ships and shipping, Undated (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Washington place names, Undated (Box-folder 13/4)
  - The Donation Land Law of Oregon, Undated (Box-folder 13/5)